now let's go over some angler
acceleration physics problems
let's start with this one a wheel speeds
up to 30 radians per second from rest in
five seconds
what is the average angular acceleration
of the wheel
so what equation do we need to calculate
the average angular acceleration
is equal to the change
in the angular velocity
divided by the change in time
so let's make a list of what we have
the initial angular speed is zero
because it speeds up from rest
the final angular speed is 30 radians
per second
and the change in time
is five seconds
so we have a change of angular speed of
30 radians per second
and we're going to divide it by five
seconds
so 30 divided by five is six
so the average angular acceleration
is six radians
per second squared
so this is the answer to the first
problem
number two
a disk slows down from 85 radians per
second to 25 radians per second in four
seconds
what is the average angular acceleration
of the disc
so let's make a list of what we know
the initial angular speed
is 85 radians per second
the final angular speed
is 25 radians per second
and the change in time is 4 seconds so
we need to use the same formula so
average acceleration is equal to the
change
and the angular velocity divided by the
change in time
so that's going to be 25
minus 85
divided by 4.
25 minus 85
is negative 60 and if we divide that by
this will give us negative 15
radians per second squared
so what is the negative sign tells us
about
the angular acceleration
the reason why it's negative is because
the disk is slowing down
now this leads to a question
if the angular acceleration can be
negative can the angular velocity be
negative
and what does that mean in terms of a
spinning disc
so the disc can spin in two ways
it could spin
in
a clockwise direction
or
it could spin
in a counterclockwise direction
we're going to assign a positive value
to the counterclockwise direction
because if you took trig
this would represent an angle of
positive 30
and this would represent an angle of
negative 30. so keeping with that we're
going to say that
a counterclockwise rotation will be
positive and a clockwise rotation will
be negative
so therefore
the angular speed or angular velocity
will be positive
when moving in the counterclockwise
direction
and negative when moving
in a clockwise direction
so for our example
at one point let's say at point a
the disc is spinning
with an angular velocity of positive
radians per second
and then after some time has elapsed
the disc is now moving
with angular velocity of positive 25
in the counterclockwise direction now
because it's slowing down that means
that
the angular acceleration has to be
negative
which means the angular acceleration is
in the opposite direction
since it's a negative 15 radians per
second squared
so notice that the angular acceleration
is directed
clockwise
and clockwise
has a negative sign
but the angular velocity is directed
counterclockwise
which has a positive sign
so that can help you to understand the
positive and negative values of the
angular velocity and
angular acceleration so if the angular
velocity is positive
it means that it's spinning in one
direction and based on the way we
assigned it it's been in
the counterclockwise direction
if the angular velocity is negative then
the disc is going to be spinning in the
clockwise direction
so hopefully that makes sense
so let's make a summary of a few key
points that we need to know
so if omega is positive
and if alpha is positive
that is if they're both directed
in the counterclockwise direction
if they both have the same sign
the disk
will speed up
it's going to spin faster and faster
in our last example
we see that the angular velocity omega
had a positive sign it was moving in a
counterclockwise direction
but alpha the angular acceleration was
negative which means it was directed
in the clockwise direction
now because these two are directed in
opposite directions
the disk
is going to slow down
so anytime
omega and alpha share the same sign if
they're both positive or both negative
the disk will speed up
if omega and alpha
contain opposite signs be it positive
and negative or negative and positive
then the disc will slow down
number three
a disc with a diameter of 30 centimeters
spins at a constant rate of 40 radians
per second
what is the linear velocity of a point
at the edge of the disc
and what is the radial acceleration of
the disc
so let's say this is the disc
and the diameter
is 30 centimeters
which means the radius
is half
of 30 so that's going to be 15
centimeters
now we're concerned about a point at the
edge of a disk
so it's 15 centimeters from the center
how can we find the linear velocity of
that point
linear velocity
is equal to omega
times r
and we have omega the angular speed
that's 40 radians per second
and then if we multiply by the radius
which is 15 centimeters but we got to
convert that to meters and we could do
that by dividing it by 100
this is going to be point 15 meters
which i like to think of it as 0.50
meters per radian
so it's 40 times 0.15
so the linear velocity
is 6 meters per second
so now that we have the linear velocity
how can we calculate the radial
acceleration
of the disk
so let's say if
the point is now located at this
position the radial acceleration
is the same as the centripetal
acceleration
it always points towards the center of
the circle
the centripetal acceleration you can
calculate it using this equation v
squared divided by r
so it's 6 squared divided by the radius
of 0.15
6 squared is 36 and 36 divided by 0.15
is 240.
so it's 240 meters per second squared
now let's move on to number four
a disc with a radius of 1.5 centimeters
speeds up from 20 radians per second
to 100 radians per second in two seconds
what is the average angular acceleration
of the disk
so how can we find the answer to this
question
well we can use the same formula as
we've been using
it's going to be the change in velocity
that is angular velocity
divided by the change in time
so the final angular speed is 100
radians per second and the initial
angular speed is 20 radians per second
and it went from 20 to 100 in two
seconds
so 100 minus 20 is 80 so that's the
change in angular speed divided by two
seconds
is going to be 40
radians per second square
so that's it for part a
now let's move on to part b
what is the centripetal acceleration of
a point at the edge of the disk when the
angular speed is 60 radians per second
so if the point is at the edge of the
disk that means that
it's 1.5 centimeters from the center of
the circle
so we can use a radius of 1.5
centimeters
so how can we calculate the centripetal
acceleration
also known as the radial acceleration
the centripetal acceleration is v
squared over r
and v is omega times r
so this is omega squared times r squared
which is r times r
and so we can use this equation
it's going to be omega square times the
radius
so we're using an angular speed of 60.
we can't use 20 or 100 because
the angular speed is not constant so
we're using the average angular speed
so it's going to be 60 squared
times the radius
which is 1.5 centimeters but if we
divide that by 100 that's 0.015 meters
60 squared is 3600 times .015
so
the centripetal acceleration is 54
radians i mean meters
per second squared
now how can we find the answer to part c
what is the net acceleration of the
point
in part b
well let's draw a picture
so let's get rid of
most of the stuff that we have here
so let's start by drawing a circle
now let's say
the point is currently at that position
at that point
there is an upward centripetal
acceleration
that points towards the center of the
circle
and the angle acceleration is positive
which means that
it's directed in the
counterclockwise direction based on the
way we defined it
so at this point
the
angle acceleration is in that direction
now we need to calculate the net
acceleration
which should be directed here
however we need to change its
value we'll need to convert that
into the tangential acceleration
to find the tangential acceleration
it's equal to the angular acceleration
times r
so the angular acceleration
is 40 radians per second squared
and the radius
is point zero
one five meters
so forty times
point zero one five
the tangential acceleration is pretty
small
it's only point six
meters per second squared
so here we have the tangential
acceleration
and now we need to use it to calculate
the net acceleration
so the net acceleration is the vector
sum of these two
so if you turn into a right triangle it
will look like this
this is the tangential acceleration
this is the centripetal acceleration
and that's the net acceleration
which is the hypotenuse of the right
triangle
so the net acceleration
we can calculate it using this formula
it's going to be the square root of the
square of the centripetal acceleration
plus the square of the tangential
acceleration
so this centripetal acceleration is 54
meters per second squared and the
tangential acceleration
is 0.6 squared
so the final answer should be close to
54 because it's much larger than 0.6
so it's going to be about 54.003
meters per second squared
so
as the disc
increases in speed
the centripetal acceleration becomes
more significant
and the tangential acceleration becomes
negligible
so if the tangential acceleration is
held constant as you increase the speed
the centripetal acceleration greatly
increases
because it depends on the square
of the speed
so if you double the speed this
centripetal acceleration increases by a
factor of four two squared is four
so at high speeds
the net acceleration
is approximately equal
to the centripetal acceleration
but at low speeds and if the object is
accelerating quickly
then the net acceleration will be
dependent on both but at very high
speeds
this becomes insignificant
so the net acceleration is almost equal
to the centripetal acceleration
you